<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | Steve Robinson]]></title>
  <link href="http://steverob.github.io/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://steverob.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-10T14:44:24+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://steverob.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steve Robinson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[steve.rob@me.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Fresh Start]]></title>
    <link href="http://steverob.github.io/blog/2014/08/10/a-fresh-start/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-10T11:04:08+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://steverob.github.io/blog/2014/08/10/a-fresh-start</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its my birthday and I&rsquo;m turning 23 today. I&rsquo;ve been meaning to start a new blog (old one <a href="http://footyntech.wordpress.com">here</a>) for a while now and I&rsquo;ve finally taken that step today. I love blogging and I encourage people around me to do it but then for several months, interestingly right after I feel in love with Ruby and Rails I&rsquo;ve stopped writing completely. I do not know why that happened but it just happened. I wrote these <em>come back posts</em> whenever I felt inspired to write something and I promised I would resume blogging but I never did. And I really don&rsquo;t know if this new blog would be any different. But I hope it is.</p>

<p>Alright why am I starting a new blog? Well, I don&rsquo;t have a proper reason for that. Its like I just don&rsquo;t feel like writing anymore over there in my old blog. Whenever I go through the old stuff I wrote, for some reason, I feel it just does not reflect who I am now. Maybe it did when I wrote them but now I think I&rsquo;ve changed a lot. So I want to start afresh with this new blog.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m Steve Robinson and I work as a technical consultant at <a href="http://sprite.com">Spritle Software</a>. I write code for a living and I write code as a hobby. Apart from software I&rsquo;m interested in football (not hand-egg), humanitarian causes, politics, aviation and computer science. I have a pet GSD and his name is <a href="http://instagram.com/p/ifq033MjsP">Jim</a> and like most programmers I know, I absolutely love coffee! I&rsquo;m a Protestant Christian and I live in a medium sized dusty town called Avadi near Chennai. This is my life :)</p>

<p>Oh and this blog is statically generated using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
